# **Matthias Minderer**

mjlm@google.com | mjlm.github.io | Google Scholar

### **Summary**

I am a researcher interested in representation learning in neural systems. During my PhD, I studied how visual and motor information is encoded in the brain. Since then, I have moved to artificial systems, focusing on how to impart abstract structure and inductive biases to the representations learned by deep neural networks. Currently, I work on adversarial methods for learning semantically meaningful visual representations without supervision.

#### Education

2012–2018 PhD in Neuroscience Harvard University

2010–2012 MSc in Neuroscience ETH Zürich

2007–2010 BA in Natural Sciences University of Cambridge

## Research experience

2018-present AI Residency

Google Brain

- Developed a model that learns unsupervised object-centric representations from video.
- Designed adversarial methods to improve self-supervised representation learning.
- Implemented semantic segmentation algorithms for medical images.

2012-2018 PhD research

Dr. Christopher Harvey, Harvard University

- Recorded and analyzed neural activity to study sensorimotor representations in mouse cortex.
- Designed deep neural network models of neural encoding and decoding.
- Developed software tools to collect, analyze and visualize neuroscience data (GitHub).

2011–2012 MSc research

ETH Zürich & Max Planck Institute for Biological Cybernetics

• Studied representations in rat motor cortex using two-photon calcium imaging.

## **Publications**

**Minderer M**, Tschannen M, Bachem O, Houlsby N. Adversarial shortcut removal for self-supervised representation learning.

In preparation.

**Minderer M**, Sun C, Villegas R, Cole F, Murphy K, Lee H. Unsupervised Learning of Object Structure and Dynamics from Videos.

NeurIPS (2019). <u>arXiv</u>

**Minderer M**, Brown KD, Harvey CD. The Spatial Structure of Neural Encoding in Mouse Posterior Cortex during Navigation.

Neuron (2019). PDF

Spaen Q, Asín-Achá R, Chettih SN, **Minderer M**, Harvey CD, Hochbaum DS. HNCcorr: A Novel Combinatorial Approach for Cell Identification in Calcium Imaging Movies.

eNeuro (2019). PDF

**Minderer M**, Brown K, Harvey CD. Unsupervised mapping of visual-motor representations in mouse cortex during navigation.

BigNeuro workshop, NIPS (2017). PDF

Driscoll LN, Pettit NL, **Minderer M**, Chettih SN, Harvey CD. Dynamic Reorganization of Neuronal Activity Patterns in Parietal Cortex.

Cell (2017). PDF

Minderer M, Harvey CD, Donato F, Moser EI. Neuroscience: Virtual reality explored.

Nature (2016). PDF

**Minderer M**, Liu W, Sumanovski LT, Kügler S, Helmchen F, Margolis DJ. Chronic imaging of cortical sensory map dynamics using a genetically encoded calcium indicator.

J Phys (2011). PDF

# Technical experience

Developed novel deep learning architectures for video prediction, visual representation learning.

Developed wide and deep models of scientific video and timeseries data (CNNs, VAEs, large linear models in Python, TensorFlow/Keras, Matlab).

Designed terabyte-scale image processing pipelines using distributed computing (LSF-managed cluster at Harvard Medical School).

Set up relational databases (MySQL) for data processing pipelines.

Developed virtual reality systems for behavioral experiments (microcontrollers, custom circuits, basic knowledge of C/C++ and OpenGL).

Designed and built custom microscopes and other optical systems (AutoDesk Inventor, Zemax).

#### Awards

2016 NVIDIA Hardware Grant

2014 Boehringer Ingelheim Fonds PhD Fellowship (PhD years 3 and 4)

2012 Herchel Smith Graduate Fellowship, Harvard University (PhD years 1 and 2)

2009 Homerton College Foundation Scholarship, University of Cambridge

#### Service

2018–present Reviewer for ICLR, ICML Workshop on Understanding and Improving Generalization in Deep Learning.

2015 Co-founded a computational methods discussion group at Harvard Medical School. Monthly meetings, 80 members as of 2018.

2014 Teaching fellow for Harvard 306qc: Quantitative Methods for Biologists. Provided introduction to MATLAB programming and statistics for incoming graduate students.

2013 Lecturer for *Science In The News*, a student-run science outreach group.

Mentor for high-school students in the *Health Professions Recruitment & Exposure Program* at Harvard Medical School.

### Relevant coursework

2017 CIFAR Reinforcement Learning Summer School

Montreal Institute for Learning Algorithms

2016 Algorithms: Design and Analysis, Part 1 online; Stanford via Coursera (certificate)

Convolutional Neural Networks for Visual Recognition online; Stanford

2015 Advanced Machine Learning Harvard CS281; Prof. Finale Doshi-Velez

2014 Machine Learning online; Stanford via Coursera

2013 Computational Neuroscience Harvard MCB 131; Prof. Haim Sompolinsky

2012 Computational Cognitive Science MIT 9.660; Prof. Josh Tenenbaum

2007–2010 Undergraduate courses in calculus, linear algebra, probability, statistics University of Cambridge